Guide to the Arthur Morris Collins Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Arthur Morris Collins papers
1889-1924
MS 147
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3
Correspondence, notebooks, examination questions, photographs and memorabilia almost all related to Collins' student years at Yale. Also included are letters from his years at the Hotchkiss School and memorabilia from his European tour in 1902. The notebooks and other papers of his son-in-law, Jeremiah H. Bartholomew, Jr., from his years at Yale College (1920-1924) are also in the papers.
Collins, Arthur Morris, 1880-1967
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jeremiah Bartholomew, Jr., 1967.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. Correspondence. II. Memorabilia.
Scope and Contents
The Arthur Morris Collins papers consist of correspondence and other materials dating from the Yale years of Arthur Morris Collins. Collins, who graduated from Yale in 1903, later changed the spelling of his name and thereafter signed himself Arthur Collens. The Papers were donated to Yale by his son-in-law Jeremiah H. Bartholomew, Jr., a 1924 Yale graduate, in 1967.
The Papers are divided into two series, CORRESPONDENCE and MEMORABILIA. CORRESPONDENCE is arranged chronologically, and consists largely of letters from members of Collins' family to him at Yale dealing with domestic matters. Also included are a selection of letters from school friends and organizations, and assorted official communications from Yale University.
MEMORABILIA is divided into four sections, each arranged chronologically. The first, Yale University, contains several notebooks (see folders 3 and 4), examination questions, printed invitations and other souvenirs of social activities, as well as Collins' Hillhouse High School, Hotchkiss School, and Yale diplomas (see Folio). Also incorporated in this section are a number of notebooks and other Yale related papers belonging to Jeremiah H. Bartholomew, Jr.
The second section, Photographs, contains twenty-one photographs, including one of Collins. Most are pictures of unidentified Yale students and other friends or possibly family members. Five photographs of New Haven have been transferred to the Yale Picture Collection.
European Tour is made up of schedules, souvenirs, and maps from Collins' trip through England, France, Germany, and Switzerland in 1902.
Finally, Miscellaneous contains memorabilia not from Collins' Yale years or his European tour. Included are a number of objects, such as the copper plate used to print his calling cards and a number of cardboard party favors.
Biographical / Historical
Arthur Morris Collins was born in Cleveland, Ohio, on November 4, 1880. After attending Hotchkiss School, from which he graduated in 1889, he went on to Yale University and graduated in 1903. In 1906 he married Annette Vailey Whipple.
He entered the investment business in New York, then moved to Hartford, Connecticut, in 1916 to organize and operate the Investment Bureau for several insurance companies. In 1921 he joined Phoenix Mutual, becoming president in 1935, a post he held until 1950. He was also a president of the Mechanics Savings Bank and a director for more than forty years, as well as being a director of the Connecticut Bank and Trust Company and of the National Fire Insurance Company.
Collins was director of the National Industrial Conference Board and the Government Research Institute, a director of the Life Insurance Association of America, and of the Institute of Life Insurance. He founded and managed the Community Chest campaigns, served on the Hartford Hospital finance commission, the advisory commission for the Connecticut Institute for the Blind, and Hartford University's Art School.
Collins died in Hartford on July 23, 1967, at the age of eighty-six.
Families; Photoprints; Bartholomew, Jeremiah H.; Collins, Arthur Morris, 1880-1967; Yale College (1887- ). Class of 1903; Yale College (1887- ). Class of 1924; Yale University -- Students
- Correspondence, 1893-1909, undated; Series I
  - 1893-1894 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1898 March-October (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1898 November-December (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1899 January-March (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1899 April-November (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1900 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1901 January-April (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1901 June-November (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1902 January-May (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1902 June (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1902 July-December (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1903 January-March (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1903 May-December (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1904-1909 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Memorabilia, 1889-1924, undated; Series II
  - Yale University
    - 1896-1898 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1898 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - [Circa 1898-1903] (Box 2, Folder 3 - 4)
    - 1899 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1900 (Box 2, Folder 6 - 7)
    - 1901 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 1902 (Box 2, Folder 9 - 10)
    - 1903 (Box 3, Folder 11 - 13)
    - 1904-1909 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Objects, [Circa 1898-1903] (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Diplomas, 1889, 1899, 1903
      General
      See: Series II. Memorabilia, 1889-1924, undated Box 5
    - Notebooks and Papers of Jeremiah H. Bartholomew, Jr.
      - 1920-1921 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - [Circa 1920-1924] (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - 1922-1923 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - 1923-1924 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - 1924 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Photographs (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - European tour
    - 1902 (Box 4, Folder 22 - 24)
    - Maps, 1902 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous
    - 1899-1910, undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Objects, Undated
  - Oversize [diplomas], 1889, 1899, 1903 (Box 5)